so I'm very pleased to welcome Lucian
preup uh from adelene and the all do
site search engine to his achievements
there uh based in Paris and was the very
kind host of a Hast stack on tour we did
uh I think end of
20222 yes which was great fun in Paris
and um
Lucien is a a stwart of the The Hite
conference has done many talks here so
we're going to hand over to him and he's
going to be talking about Apache Lucine
and the journey from text indexing to
artificial intelligence
Lucen uh yes hello um so thank you for
being here uh it's uh so nice to to find
you again um so I have some questions
for you uh
um so yeah I know we are also online but
for for people we are here physically
present how many of you are luing
committers in this room okay so we have
one person here so yeah thank you for
everything you do um how many of you
work with a solar elastic search open
search so with Lucine in some
way okay so like your maybe three third
uh three yeah three quarters and um how
many of you are like with other search
Technologies I like algolia like we8
pine cone or something else okay so a
few people yeah great thanks uh so um
yeah no need to to introduce this uh
more than that but Lucine is a search
technology
a very powerful search
technology uh and what's interesting
about Lucine what's amazing about L
Lucine is that uh it was um first
incubated into the Apachi project in
2001 uh which is really really
um amazing uh I am not aware of another
technology that has uh such a long
lifespan Maybe all the technologies that
we are using
today half of them have less than three
years uh technologies that we used five
years ago are no longer used
anymore uh there was a time where we
talked about much about for example Hado
or other things like that which
technology is still there but we don't
like see the same the same
traction um and I don't I don't talk
about like uh front end technologies
that like come and go really quickly so
22 year and a half and
Counting um and yeah that's
that's
like so uh um amazing um like looking
back to the to the to the life of pach
Lucine
um these are some citations that I took
from Twitter uh
so by the way Twitter
uses Apachi Apachi Lucin for for its
search internal search they were even
committers in the beginning and they
were extensively using apach
line uh so yeah Twitter didn't exist
when aach was funded but these are
tweets from 2011 and so on and what we
see are a lot of work that has been done
throughout the time by the community and
by the committers on um performance we
see a lot of things that all of the
sudden go like 100 times faster 50 times
faster five times faster any faster any
in any proportion we also see aulus in
finding bugs in the G jvm it's maybe the
the project that that has found the most
bugs in the
jvm um and yeah it continues since since
the beginning of Twitter
even uh and yeah the last one is talking
about vectors which is something that
was um in the
hype last year and the year
before yeah um I don't know if you know
this conference how many of you know
about Burling bzw wordss in the room
okay great so it's it's a European
conference that uh that takes place in
Berlin and it's the reference for
everything search store and scale mainly
in the open source world and uh since
quite a lot a long time we see each year
uh a talk around apach luine either
what's new in apach luine or how many
bugs apach luin find found this year in
the jvm or uh how did we test and
improve the performance and so on and um
I am actually ready to bet that in 2031
30 years from
2001 uh we will see
someone that will talk about pul and
Berlin B wordss
um so
yeah aach it's actually uh powering a
lot of Technologies uh we don't talk
much about Apachi Notch these days but
it was powered by Apachi seen also aach
is like the the
the the technology that came right
before
hop um we of course have Apache solar
that's uh
that's was even like merged with Apache
Lucine from some for some time uh we
have of course elastic search but we
also have uh some newer Technologies
mongodb actually chose chose aach luine
to build their uh search capabilities so
it's like choices that were made like
two years ago so we are still like
choosing aach luine for new projects
it's not like a it's it's a it's it's a
it's a technology that's uh that's there
because it has a large number of
users um I didn't introduce myself so
I'm I'm Lucian I work with a company
called adelan and we do everything
around Consulting training we also
develop a software that's called A2 and
it's built with apach luine
also um and yeah Charlie mentioned all.
site which is a collaborative search
engine that's also built with apach
underneath now let's take a step back
and see how how we got there how apach
um manag to
reinvent not necess necessarily reinvent
wheel but reinvent itself throughout the
the time throughout the years um
so the basis of a patulin is the
inverting in index I'm sure you already
know about that and I just wanted to
like re uh focus on that because this is
how it started I take here three
documents uh and the first thing that
aulus in does with those is um the
tokenization
so it extracts words I mean they are not
really words they are tokens but uh I in
a simplified uh version we can say that
they are words then we keep the unique
words we sort them and then we list them
and this is the inverted Index this is
the very first version of Lucine it's an
exercise that you can give to to a a
student at University or to to a
candidate that that comes from for a job
interview or even to chat GPT uh it will
be able to to write this program so this
was the for the first version we have
also something that's uh really um a
core functionality of a bachelin which
is the the analysis chain okay so
actually these tokens are not put into
the index as they are they are
transformed through an analysis chain so
you see that we have have capitals here
so we lowercase them you can see that we
have for example cars which is plural
automobile which is uh not it's is
singular so we can do something around
stemming for example we can also uh
provide synonyms this is something that
arrived later but uh it's something that
that's that's available so we can say
automobile and car is the same thing and
and so on we can also like use what we
call stop wordss because we see that
some words uh like 2D of on are actually
checking all the marks they are
retrieving all the documents so we
consider them like non-relevant for the
index and we get to something like this
and this type of structure is really uh
um
optimized for
um uh performance and it's also
optimized for Boolean qu queries if I
search for example for for automobile
the answer is right really fast I I can
go directly to the pointer to the
documents that correspond to my search
query in this case is document one
document two if I search for France I
find another set of documents which is
document two and document three and then
doing the intersection of two these two
sets is is really fast so all the bull
and queries are really fast with a
patulin this is what what's the
technolog is built for in reality there
are some other structures that are there
because we also like need some metadata
we also need to support um phrases and
uh stuff like that so in reality even
the first versions were a little bit
more complex than
this uh so yeah we can this this syntax
is still available today it's still
available in in user interfaces like
kibana and op search dashboards um and
and yeah you you could do like search on
a field you could do
like um phrase search you know so
positions you could do like FY search
approximate you can do
approximate on a
phrase uh and so on um some of these
were not available in the beginning we
will see about that uh I talked about
the the text analysis this is also
something that's fundamental in in
Lucine and it's
the fact that we can analyze the text at
index time and and in the same time at
query time this is something that's that
makes
the uh aach so so powerful so actually
the the two the two
Transformations uh find themselves
together in the in the index and uh yeah
this is why it works so
fast this is an example of an autoc
completion service and we start to to
see where it's going so actually apin
calculates a lot of things at index time
in order to be fast at search time so uh
for example Auto completion back in the
days it was done with uh like um wild
cards uh this was the way to do it this
means that we have to scan all the index
and yeah
uh we introduced engrams and um
this made the index a lot
bigger uh but that was not necessarily
an issue when it became an issue then
Lucine introduced uh the compressing of
the index and we finally even with
engrams in the index we end ended up
like an index that has the size of the
original text
file while also embarking a lot of a lot
of functionality in it so the analysis
change
can be different at uh per time at and
an index time and it's it allows us to
do a plenty of interesting
stuff okay in this example yeah we have
an analysis that's active that's the
same at query time and this one is
different at query time so the
functionality is slightly different so
we have
a a different Behavior just to site also
apach is solar in this stock uh you have
a nice interface in the in the Solar
dashboard that actually allows you to
debug what's happening with your with
your text and prior to this interface we
had other tools that that allows to to
debug allow allowed to debug what what
was happening into
into um
Lucine I mentioned in the beginning uh
there was a citation that was saying
that Lucine is a 100 times faster for f
fuzzy queries and actually uh this is
not not only fzy queries there was like
a a big wave of uh changes that came
into Lucine that were FSA and
fsts um and this was really a game
changer so this was the functionality
this was the the the structure that made
fuzzy queries so so much more uh uh
performing so we we really had like a
100 times faster uh queries following to
this and this structure was later like
uh pushed through uh a lot of uh a lot
of um other functionalities of of Lucine
so this goes in the same direction uh
like building the index with all the
necessary data uh that's needed for
example this graph here represents the
mod the the word dogs uh and it's it's
huge just like the engr
earlier uh and this is why it's it's
limited to two character of distance but
nevertheless it's uh it's really a great
Improvement in performance to have
something like a 100 times faster and it
was really a game
changer for following to that or not
necessarily following to that apach
Lucin was used a lot in e-commerce and
uh we soon realized that um we also need
numbers uh apach Lucin was a text
technology it didn't support numbers in
the
beginning uh if you wanted to for
example sort like in this example sort
the the prices uh you really needed to
use strings and to pad them with zeros
in order the sort to be correct um so
yeah adding numbers was also a challenge
and it was like taken by by apach and it
was it was implemented really really
really well uh I I not aware of all the
details but for example integers are not
stored in the um usual manner but they
are stored like
um um to to to gain space
and then we had also uh coming from
e-commerce in the beginning the facets
so we needed term facets range facets
hierarchical facets and we realized that
we have to invert the to invert the
inverted index quite often uh to to
build a structure that's called field
cache and actually this was the
beginning of what we call Doc values
which is actually another structure
that's a pumer database um that's um
also embedded into a
p data store uh and with this uh came a
lot of use cases as we will see later we
even have uh like features related to
relational databases where we could uh
really do PR time joints with a puline
there are two features that are really
great for e-commerce which is the the
nested uh the documents so the document
block and the field collapsing
collapsing also that was introduced
quite early in aulus so eCommerce was
driving a lot the the features of aach
luine and then we had um Maps uh so uh
all
the uh polygon searches and all that
were quite slow in the beginning because
they were using integers so numbers
which are which are not the best
structure to store for polygons and
points in order to to calculate for
example that a point a latitude
longitude is within a c for example uh
we needed to like go through all the
points and calculate distances and stuff
like that and then came
the
the um Geo shapes and the the the geob
bounding box query and all all the stuff
around that which made actually Lucine
become uh the most uh used uh and and
maybe the best uh spatial
database and with that uh this brings us
to all the use cases that you might know
around monitoring and observability and
use cases that today make maybe 80 if
not 90% of use cases of elastic search
and maybe also open search so like
80% of his cases of
apach and we all know where it where
where it ended I mean it's it's not
ended yet but it's it contined and and
it's actually taken like another another
direction from there and then we had uh
vectors that came on we said okay but I
need
a I need um I'm sorry that you cannot
see the links here on the screen but
i i i site my sources so this comes from
the from elastic um they do some nice
animations there so so we needed we
needed uh we needed semantic we needed
vectors uh so um we had a paradigm shift
with the with all the vector search
there and we introduced vectors so I
will go quite Qui quickly around this
because you've already seen the the
presentation this morning that was more
presented so the the presentation about
hybrid search uh so what are vectors uh
they are actually
a vector space representation of of text
but it also introduces uh multimodality
so you can also uh use uh image search
and audio search uh because you just
need to use a machine learning model
that knows to um construct the same
structure out of text audio and video
and uh you can get uh what we call uh a
vector so for those of you that do not
know how it works the the vectorization
here so here's a simple example of a
three dimensional Vector it's just three
dimension you have size friendliness and
intelligence and we try to categorize
any object whatsoever an image a text an
audio file
whatsoever uh um compared to these axes
so we have three here in reality vectors
have thousands of of axes or or at least
hundreds
um so yeah for example a cat would rate
in size 025 compared to an elephant
which is 090
90 and so
on uh and then all the documents in our
index are placed into a vector space uh
and um when we come with a new document
which is our query we will just find the
nearest the nearest
neighbors so as I said this allowed to
do multimodel search and uh this is how
the vector search is working we take the
documents in the input we construct the
vector representation of these documents
and then uh we do the same thing with
the query we have to use the same model
or a model that knows to uh to to treat
the query as a query and we compare then
the the the vectors of the query with
the vectors that's are available in the
index at first we had K&N which is kind
of a Brute Force approach and then we
introduced approximate Cann uh and um
which
allowed a faster
um um
faster approach to to to vector vector
search and it it continued it continued
we had a Canon with filters which is
also a feature uh and yeah this is the
first step to hybrid search and as you
saw in the talk this morning for those
that that that followed it uh yeah we if
we need Vector s we need hybrid search
and if we need hybrid search we luine is
a is is a good
choice We Al have a support for sparse
uh vectors which is a different uh
structure that is
um
um like more uh more easy to maintain
and um which is uh compatible to the
inverted index that uh that Apache
already has so uh this is an ability
that uh we do not see often uh so we can
support both of them both dense and
sparse and uh which is which is great so
this is an example of term expansion
which is used for sparse vectors uh so
it's actually similar to what you saw in
the um fuzzy fuzzy query where it
construct a graph of all the
possible uh combinations of of a a term
yeah so we
survived Geo search columnar
databases Vector
search
um and then we had
uh CH
GPT um which was actually kind of a game
changer how many of you are using chat
GPT
as a search engine instead of a search
engine you go to chat GPT to ask a
question instead of going to Google okay
so you are quite a lot uh
so was this the the end of of some
changes was it was was this the end of
the of a pat you also as a search
engine uh there was a lot of debate when
when it started um we actually moved
from this
which was like the search engine that
was uh putting everything on relevance
and personalization everything
on doing
what's in my I mean doing what's what's
capable of doing to to to give you the
best result um and we move to to this
actually uh I don't know how many of you
are using Bing uh maybe you're not many
because because you're using you switch
from Google to chat GPT directly uh but
this is the new Bing so it's actually no
longer like I'm feel ly like this with
with just one search results which
supposingly is the one that contains my
my answer it's actually a chatbot
powered by a technology that's called
co-pilot and it's based on chat
GPT um yeah so just taking a step back
we we kind of saw that coming uh just
Charlie was mentioning h on Tour Paris
we had this meeting this tour this this
conference in November 2022 it was just
one week before chat GPT was released we
didn't know that it it was coming and uh
when the audience asked so what's what's
the next for for what's the future of
the search engines uh we kind of saw
that uh the future is somewhere around
question answering because we we said we
said that search engines give you
results a list of results and it's up to
you to click on the one that's the most
relevant for you in the first page maybe
or maybe in the second page if you go
there um and then open that result and
read it summarize it understand it and
search the response you're looking for
in that document so when you actually
use you're when you're using a search
engine you're not looking for a list of
results list of possible links to the
answer to your query you're actually
looking for for an answer and Google
understood that and introduced this
question answering uh feature uh quite
early uh right after they invented the
Transformers the the Transformers were
something that was was invented by
Google and allowed chat GPT to to to pop
up later
on um and yeah you had this thing coming
and then you had also beinging that was
doing things differently but kind of
better I think because if you notice
here you have the same answer but uh you
have that um note there according to
five sources so instead of like doing
like Google like take the the one that
I'm feeling lucky I'm taking just the
first result and summarize it and give
you the answer I will take like five
results compare them like find the best
one and and so
on okay so moving back to back to llms
and CH
GPT actually we realized very quickly
that there are two problems with that um
one is that we have no knowledge into a
specific area uh we have a lot of
knowledge globally but not something
specific and we also don't don't have
realtime knowledge and the second
problem is hallucinations these models
are trained to produce words no matter
what um and yeah they give answer
answers not necessarily proven sources
uh and that's the first uh that that's
the second
problem uh yeah so I'm guess you all you
are all aware of that so this is the no
real time knowledge if you ask GPT GPT
4 uh what's what happened in
2022 uh yeah I don't know if you know
this date this is something that's
important for the British
guys um yeah CH gbt doesn't have the
answer and also if you're asking
something very specific on a specific
domain that's maybe a domain that you
know uh CH GPT will not be able to
answer because uh yeah maybe this domain
is not that well represented on on the
internet and then you have
hallucinations uh as I said uh llms will
try to answer no matter what so you can
ask like any question and you can even
have uh like questions that really do
not have an answer or questions that are
wrong in the first place but you will
have an answer that's that looks
convincing and uh it's actually not the
right one and then you have also the
problem
that as it is an llm will not be able to
tell you where it has found that answer
so which is which is a problem because
you don't know if it's if it's fake news
or if it's something that should be
taken into
account and we get on uh rag retrieval
augmented Generations so you have seen
already a lot of talks around this
subjects there are also a lot of talks
tomorrow and and this afternoon on this
subject and this is actually the
solution to the problems llms have and
also
the let's say the the future of Ain
because as you can see you need a vector
database in this solution you actually
have a user query that will not go to
the llm directly it will go to a search
engine first
and then go to the llm that receives the
question and also a context and the
context
contains things that are hopefully
relevant for the right response in the
end I just wanted to mention also uh the
keynote that we had last year uh which
was really insightful and we were
actually talking about CH GPT and it was
Granger that presented um a prompt that
allowed Chad GPT to site its sources
which was something that was not doing
by
default uh and back then uh rag and
retrieval of M generation didn't even
have a name so I will say yeah thanks to
to to hyack and I mean we are really
discussing here things that are in
advance to to our domain and uh yeah
this is this is really great as I said
this was rag but it was not called drag
back
then yeah so coming back to search
engines of course you have
uh um you have
the question answering and quite soon uh
if you see the thing on the right there
uh being introduced CH GPT directly into
the
um into the search engine so I mean just
to explain how much of a revolution that
that that was and that is actually so
the fact that we are moving away from
search engines to llms it's it's really
something that's happening um so the
first versions of beinging were kind of
bad because they they gave responses and
the um
the the llm was not really um
let's say um
um it could like answer wrong to the to
the user and all that and actually uh
The Prompt that um Bing was using was
improved and it it makes uh it it's a
prompt that that has like three pages of
of instructions there and uh so yeah
being tells it's it was called Sydney
being tells CHT to behave correctly to
to uh to not to um to use like U not to
be mean and all that uh and yeah so this
prompt here actually resembles a lot to
the one that uh Dr rer showed which is a
lot smaller but it does the job so as
you can see here you have the the
sources that are cited so the llm gives
a response but also it's documented with
search results actually these are search
results just represented in a different
manner
okay so yeah we arrived to something
like this this is the the new being you
ask a question you get the answer you
also have links to
the to the source of
the to the source of the of that answer
and actually this is the same thing that
gp4 implemented when when it goes to the
internet and retrieves data if you tell
it to do so
okay so where does aach Lucine stand uh
so you have
um
um the rag pattern and yeah I plac the
pulin here on top of your business data
because if you look at the
um internet your business data is not on
the internet your slack channels are not
on the internet your Wiki is not on the
internet so you really need
uh a technology like aach luine to index
something that the internet cannot
cannot
access uh something that Bing will not
have access
to uh and uh yeah even if you're using
for example Microsoft or for Enterprise
you will always have systems that are
not taken into account for example if
you have withan in addition to to
Microsoft for example you will still
need something in between to to index
all those all those data sources and to
to build your own rank system as we also
saw some of the conferences
here okay so uh I also have a yes we
don't have much time um I also have like
a small demo it's not not much but I I
I I we don't have much time I just want
to point you to the to this uh
presentation that my colleagues will do
at open search conference uh uh next
month uh which will actually like go
through all the details of how you can
Implement a rug system with Apachi luine
uh from A to
Z uh I will try to maybe bring up a demo
a quick demo we have three minutes left
uh on elastic search this for this time
uh just to G credit to
everyone uh yeah so just before we leave
uh let me just uh switch to this short
demo I will go directly to the end of
the
demo uh can we see
it yeah I'm sorry okay so here it is
okay so this is a this is um like a
small system that was built on top of
this data uh that are
here uh so actually yeah in this demo we
go through all
the vector search and uh machine
learning and and implementing a reg
system so we have all the all the talks
that are uh that
are available on the on the HTO
homepage
um I just one I need to show you uh how
many uh documents we have here so we
have 20 20 talks here and yeah they are
all here and just on top of that I will
show you if you have we have time the
details if not we have also the
lightning talks there after afterwards
so when you ask questions like this for
example you get search results but they
are actually presented in the in a
conversational manner okay so how it
goes you need as as we saw in the
presentation you need to I'll go
directly to the to the vector
one
demo okay so this is the indexing part
uh this is the pipeline that allows my
data to get
vectorized uh this is the Target Field
which is al already configured uh with
the mapping specific M mapping this is
the model ID that I that I downloaded
from hugging phas and then I reindex my
data to the Target
index and then I can ask questions
like like this one for
example which is a just a vector query I
also have examples of hybrid queries and
yeah for example here I I search for
artificial intelligence and I have
things that that are related with that
not necessarily uh they not necessarily
mentioned artificial intelligence as
keywords they mention for example AI or
something within those lines and you
have a you have a the
answer okay so yeah this is a talk that
will be here in this room tomorrow so
yeah that's all for me um
and uh yeah uh it's loading it's just
uh yeah this is the thank you screen so
thanks thank you ly okay so uh I'm going
to kick off with a question from our
online audience Tor has a question
uh and this is a quite a general
question but what are some best
practices for using both vector and
keyword-based retrieval at the same
time yes uh I I wouldn't say that uh
there are best practices uh if if you
uh saw the the talk that uh that was
here this morning about uh about hybrid
search exactly uh it was actually
mentioning it was really interesting so
take a look at the video when it's when
it's out um it was actually mentioning
the use cases that you have and
depending on the use cases that you have
you will implement the the right hybrid
search but the bottom line is that
hybrid search is
almost every time use useful so uh we
yeah we difficultly can find use cases
where just pure Vector search is enough
okay thank you any questions from the
floor a question right at the back
okay thank you for the talk it's very
nice to see how Lucine is evolving uh
you mentioned some user experience and I
would even say user interface
considerations in the difference between
how being present results when you do
retrial augmented but one to show the
sources and let the users have their own
understanding uh can you speak a bit
about how um Lucen implementations have
evolved in term of user experience and
user interfaces and do you see this uh
changing over the next days or next
years as we see user interfaces having
an impact on how people can leverage rag
for actual
actions yeah thanks thanks for your
question so actually aart you luine is a
is a lowlevel library that provides all
the tools for you to implement on top of
it and that goes also for solar elastic
search open search that are built on top
of elastic on top of aine they are not
actually providing user
interfaces uh but that being said uh you
can
um uh let me just uh go back you can so
with this pattern here you see that the
parine needs to be there to provide with
the vector search and mostly with hybrid
search also uh most important and this
allows you to have interfaces like this
for example where you give the answer
but you also give links to the data that
contains uh the information that
provided the
answer so the interface the user
interface is actually up to you up to
your application you can implement it
like this or or uh or or U like this for
example so it's it's something that's uh
that's that's up to to every application
but um
um a we just we just provide the the
tool so specifically the hybrid
search just like to add to that I mean
the interesting thing is I this this
reminds me of the fact we we did
actually plan a a ux for search and AI
Workshop uh for hastac and sadly
unfortunately our Workshop teer had a
pull out due to some family health
issues so we had a councel a workshop
but it's something we're looking to
quite a lot at OC and I'm not sure we
all give enough consideration to the
user experience when we're building
search applications I suspect a lot of
us here are backend people and and not
great you know not not so focused on
that area but I think it's something we
need to look at more because we are
seeing radical changes in how people are
using search backed
applications um it's moving a lot it's
moving away from 10 Blue Links and I
think this is something we need to take
more account of so yeah maybe there will
some more more on that over the next
year we have any other questions
foran and the new the new search engines
kind of look like this now so it's more
like a chatbot then then or an assistant
or or a co-pilot then then what we used
to call a search engine
before okay well we have no more
questions from online so please put your
hands get a pollution thank you